A very good evening to you ladies and
gentlemen. We can do better. A very good
evening to you ladies and
gentlemen. Oh wow. It's an absolute joy,
honor and pleasure to be here this
evening. Let me kick this evening off
with a favorite story of mine.
There was a little boy about 6 years old
who came to a balloon seller who was
selling balloons on the
street and he asked the balloon seller,
"Uncle, will this red balloon go up in
the
air?" The balloon seller said, "Of
course it will." Said, "And the blue
one?" 100% it will. The pink one, most
certainly it will. And you know how kids
can be. They can ask funny questions and
I give funny answers as well. A
4-year-old once came to a shopkeeper and
said to the shopkeeper girl, he said,
"Uncle, fouryear-old girl." The
shopkeeper
said, he said
uncle. The shopkeeper
uncle
children very innocent, charming,
clever, smart. They can ask funny
questions and they can give funny
answers too. A teacher in class asked a
six-year-old which state of India are
you from? He said I'm from Arunachal
Pradesh madam. She said can you spell it
for me? He said I'm from Goa
actually. Who spells Arunachal
Pradesh? Kids are kid are kids aren't
they? This little boy asked will the
pink balloon go up? Will the red balloon
go up? Will the black balloon go up?
Will the blue balloon go up? The
exasperated balloon seller said, "Look,
darling." The balloons don't go up in
the air based on their
colors. The balloons go up in the air
based on what's filled inside of them,
the gas, the air. That's what takes the
balloons to the heights of success.
Boys and
girls, the class of
2023, we are all different colored
balloons with different abilities,
different skill sets, different
backgrounds, different
upbringings, different family cultures,
different traditions, different
opportunities, different resources,
different
challenges. We all have a very different
outside.
But guess what? Everybody who has
reached the heights of success and has
made a mark in the world hasn't ever
done it based on the color of the
balloon. Hasn't ever done it based on
resources. Hasn't ever done it based on
opportunities. Hasn't ever done it based
on skills. Hasn't ever done it based on
what they've just learned in school,
college, and universities.
These are all the colors of the balloons
and extremely
important. Everybody who's left a mark
in the world and has made the world a
better place are the ones who had the
right kind of gas filled inside their
balloons. As we sort our outside, it is
very very crucial and important to fix
our inside because only those who have
their inside sorted and inside
fixed have reached
high in high up in the sky. Which is why
don't they say it's not our
aptitude but our attitude that decides
our altitude in our life? Yes. Yes. We
definitely we definitely need aptitude.
Our schools, our universities, our
teachers have given us the aptitude. But
along with that they've also given us
the right attitude by their own example.
Our families have given us the right
attitude by their own
example. When you see an
iceberg, you see only the tip of the
iceberg on the surface of the water.
Don't we? The achievements of others,
their success, their popularity, their
achievements, their accolades, their
wealth, their money, their fancy cars,
their homes, their fancy vacations and
holidays is all the tip of the iceberg.
What we
see. But right underneath that surface
is a huge humongous iceberg which is
unseen to the eyes of the world. The
world sees the tip of the iceberg. The
money, the popularity, the success, the
achievements. What we do fail to see is
the huge
iceberg underneath the surface of the
water. The failures, the patience, the
determination, the grit, the courage,
the troubles, the struggles, the
resilience, the tenacity.
All of these is what makes that little
tip sustainable and seen to the world.
As you are now going to embark on your
new journey and as you work on achieving
that tip of the iceberg, my prayer today
is that may you never forget the unseen.
Take inspiration from your heroes, from
your role models, from your families,
from your
teachers and learn. There's a humongous
iceberg underneath that surface of the
water that's responsible for the tip of
the iceberg to remain there. Remember
always, it takes a lot of sleepless
nights to become an overnight success.
And therefore, and therefore, here's the
first principle that I want to share
with all of you today. If you want to
get the
scene, focus and work on the unseen. If
you want the tip to be up there, focus
on the huge iceberg underneath the
surface. If you want your balloon, the
beautiful colored balloon to soar high
up, focus on what's filled inside as
well. How many of you love going on a
holiday? All of us. How many of you love
traveling? Oh, okay. I must put my hand
down. I hate
traveling because in a year sometimes I
end up taking over 300 to 325
flights. That's insanity when it comes
to traveling. And you can have all kinds
of experiences when you travel. Like I
was flying once and the stew artist
comes up to me. I'm not going to mention
the airline. Mr. comes up to me and
says, "Well, come on board, sir. We
guarantee
takeoff." I said, "Landing,
madam." She said, "You're a monk, isn't
it? It's important to
pray." Oh,
takeoffs and
landings. The three biggest fears people
had back in the day were number one, the
fear of public speaking. Anybody
here? Okay. Number two was the fear of
death. Anybody here? Okay. Number three
was the fear of flying on an airplane. I
guess that's why they call an airport a
terminal.
Possibly.
Possibly. Oh, and those three fears have
now been replaced with three biggest
fears today. Number one, battery of the
smartphone
dying. Number two, poor Wi-Fi signal.
And number three, that we learn your
phone, which says still buffering when
you're watching a Netflix
show. Ladies and gentlemen, boys and
girls, in my experience of travel, I
hate
travel because it's just so much of it.
But how long can you keep saying, "I
hate it. I hate it. I hate it." I don't
know when do we stop the selfdefeating
talk. I hate this subject. I hate
leaving home. I hate going here. I hate
doing this. I hate I hate I hate I hate
the selfdefeating talk stops us from
reaching where we want to reach in our
lives. Uh I I have traveled to the
United States. I said I I said right I'm
like do insane stuff. I am an insane
guy. I I remember going to the US once,
flying to New York City and then going
to Orlando for a talk.
I was in the US for 16
hours. I flew for 22 hours to be in the
US for 16 hours and got back to Mumbai
for another function. And in 6 days
after that, I flew back to New York City
17 1/2 hours to be there for 48 hours
and come back again for a function in
Mumbai. 3 days after that I flew back
again to
Chicago to be there for 36
hours to come back to Mumbai and at the
immigration there was an afroamerican
gentleman sitting there he said why
don't you just stay young man you're
just zipping in and out all the time and
guess what I
learned when you're traveling so much 17
and 1/2 hours of
flight Mumbai to New
York. We are all looking forward to
reach the destination when the flight
lands. But in looking forward to the
destination, very often, ladies and
gentlemen, boys and girls, you forget to
enjoy the journey. What a sheer waste of
17 and a half hours. If I say I hate
flying, I don't hate this. I hate being
on the flight. I hate this food on the
flight. I hate being on the seat. I hate
I hate I hate and I only be happy when I
land and I'm in New York City. I have
wasted 17 and a half hours of my
precious time. I have wasted my
journey. What I want to share with all
of you is we move from one point to
another point. Go from one destination
to another. You came here in the
kindergarten. You moved to grade
one. Destination point A to B. In
between the journey was 365 days. And
you've been moving from one destination
to another. Today at the school is your
final
destination. You move out now looking
forward to your next destination at
Colombia, at NYC, at Yale, at Stanford,
at
Oxford. And what I do want to share with
all of you is destinations are
important but do not forget to enjoy the
journey because the journey to the
destination is very long and I've seen a
lot of times that we become destination
addicts and forget to enjoy. How many of
you had a great time at
DIS? How many of you had a great time
with your
friends? How many of you enjoyed the
journey? Okay. Wow. I looks like I need
to take my clothes off and come back
madam to
Edis to experience this beautiful
journey. I was sharing with her an
interesting story. This is a class in
London 7year-olds and a teacher asked
all the kids what do you want to be when
you grow
up? Some of them said doctors, some of
them said lawyers. Some of them said
actors, some of them said
solicitors. One boy was quiet. The
teacher turned to the boy and said,
"Does it take that long to answer that
question?" Very thoughtfully, the boy
said, "When I grow up, madam, I want to
be
happy." The teacher said,
"Boy, looks like you haven't got the
question right."
The seven-year-old said,
"Ma'am, looks like you haven't got life
right." Because if you would have gotten
life right, you would know that
everything that we do is wanting to be
happy. And this answer was given by the
legendary John Lennon of the Beatles
crew. Right? It was John Lennon who said
this, "You didn't get life right. And
therefore as you move from one
destination to another do not forget to
enjoy the journey and be happy. How many
of you failed in any exam ever in your
life? Okay. Some courageous souls
raising their
hands. A boy was once walking with his
dad collegegoing boy and his friend
messaged him said our Costco college
results are going to be out very soon.
The boy messaged back saying, "I'm
walking with
dad." If he picks the phone up and he
sees I failed in a subject, I'll be
taken for a task. So, let's communicate
in code language. If I fail in one
subject, say good morning to you. I'll
understand. If you if I fail in two, say
good morning to you and dad. I'll
understand. A couple of minutes back, he
got a message saying good morning to
you, dad, family, and friends.
Ladies and gentlemen, boys and
girls, we all have had our own failures.
We all have had our own
disappointments. And as you embark on
this new journey, you'll have
yours. Life is what it is. With all our
dreams, with all our aspirations, with
all our ambitions, life does what it
does to us. And when failures do come,
disappointments do come, we need
something very incredible. I remember
when I was graduating and I was
finishing my diploma in
engineering, I stood second in the state
of
Maharashtra and I missed my first
rank by four
marks. I was very very
disappointed. I came back home bit with
tears in my eyes and it is at that time
I remember my father coming in patting
on my back and said look dear son people
will forget the grades and people will
forget the marks at the end of it all
what matters is to keep that
spark
alive we need somebody to help us keep
that spark alive borrow a glass of
water.
Thank you so much.
You know
something? All of us in us have the
spark. All of us. That spark to do
something, that spark to make a
difference, that spark to succeed, that
spark to soar
high. And this is what life does to us.
dunks
us in a glass of
water. This is what life did to me when
I wanted
to stand
first. I was disappointed. I lost my
first rank in the state of Maharashtra
for four
marks. And what life does to us kills
that spark
within. This is what life does.
extinguishes the
spark. Sometimes we feel I just can't
keep going. I can't do it. I can't I
feel
helpless. It's at those
times that we need
somebody to trigger that
spark back within us.
If you don't have this
somebody, we'll be lost. For me, it was
my
dad. And I hate saying it. I disagreed
with him. I didn't speak to him for two
full
years. He had to fall on my feet and
say, "Sorry, son." For whatever I did, I
didn't say you're sorry. My father left
in the year 2009. And every single year
I felt I'll go and
say, "Sorry,
Dad. I shouldn't have put you through
this." He was the one who stood by me to
light me up. And I in my young Zeal and
in my young enthusiasm to achieve and be
who I
was was very rude.
very rude to the same
people who light us
up. The graduating class of
2023, when life takes the spark off, you
will need
someone. Is it your mom, your dad, your
teachers, your mentors, your guides,
your friends? Find somebody who will
light you up. That is the third thing I
would like to share with you this
evening. And here's
the last little
thing, the
light. Since I fly so much, if the store
doesn't come up for that day, I'd
probably end up making the announcements
myself. If there be a lack of oxygen
supply in the
caveman, oxygen masks will deploy from
the panel above your head.
Pull the mask sharply to activate the
flow of oxygen. Secure the mask on your
face and nose and breathe normally. Make
sure your mask is in place before you
help children, infants or others. It is
very important to put our mask in place
before we can put the mask on somebody
else. Mark Twain said something very
interesting. He said there are two most
important days in life. One is the day
when we were born and second is the day
we find out why we were born in this
world. You were all born to make a
difference. You were all born to be
change makers. You were all born to be a
catalyst of change in the sometimes dark
world that we live in. But do remember
if you don't have your mask on, you
wouldn't be able to put the mask on
anybody else's face at all. And which is
why as you achieve, as you grow, as you
make your balloon soar high in the sky,
as you make sure that the tip of your
iceberg is up
there, do not forget to care for
yourself. You deserve more than what
you're giving yourself. more respect,
more love, more time, more kindness,
more compassion. And when you receive
all of that, you will definitely be in a
position to share it with others. So,
graduating class of 2023, number one,
work on the unseen so that the scene can
soar high up. Graduating class of
2023. Lesson number two, do not forget
to be happy during the journey because
the journey can be a long one until we
reach our destination. Lesson number
three, always have somebody when you
lose it to bring that spark back again
in you. And my last parting thing, make
sure your oxygen mask is in place
because you have a bright future to make
a difference in this world by being
impactful.
[Music]